<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon, preached Sept. 28, 1692, at a primary visitation held at Chichester by the Right Reverend Father in God Robert Lord Bishop of Chichester by Edw. Pelling ...</title>
            <author>Pelling, Edward, d. 1718.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53982</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1103</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20716</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12610731</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12610731</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64350</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53982)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64350)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 771:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon, preached Sept. 28, 1692, at a primary visitation held at Chichester by the Right Reverend Father in God Robert Lord Bishop of Chichester by Edw. Pelling ...</title>
                  <author>Pelling, Edward, d. 1718.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Will. Crooke ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Grove, Robert, 1634-1696.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Timothy, 1st, IV, 16 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64350:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON, Preached <hi>Sept.</hi> 28. 1692. at a <hi>Primary Viſitation</hi> Held at CHICHESTER BY THE Right Reverend Father in God ROBERT Lord Biſhop of <hi>CHICHESTER.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Publiſhed at the Biſhop's Requeſt.</p>
            <p>By <hi>EDW. PELLING,</hi> D. D. Chaplain in Ordinary to Their Majeſties, And Rector of <hi>Petworth</hi> in <hi>Suſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Will. Crooke,</hi> at the <hi>Green-Dragon</hi> without <hi>Temple-Bar,</hi> 1693.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:64350:2"/>
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Octob. 29. 1692.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Guil. Lancaſter, <hi>R. P. D.</hi> Hen. Ep. Lond. a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cris Domeſt.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:64350:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Reverend the Lord Biſhop of <hi>Chicheſter.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>COnſidering the long Happineſs I have had at <hi>London,</hi> one While in your Neighbourhood, always in your Friendſhip, your Lordſhip will eaſily believe it is no little Comfort to me, that in this part of the Kingdom my Old Acquaintance is at laſt my Dioceſan, and once again my Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour.</p>
            <p>Your Lordſhip knows, that (were there nothing elſe to be conſidered) my Affections to you are a ſufficient Security for my Obedience to your Commands: And for that Reaſon, I preſume, it was, that your Lordſhip hath been pleaſed to command me, firſt to preach your Viſitation-Sermon, and now to publiſh it. The Veneration I have for your Character and Perſon, makes me ready to obſerve your Pleaſure in all Particulars; though I muſt confeſs, that in Publiſhing this mean Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe,
<pb facs="tcp:64350:3"/> I comply with your Lordſhip's Will with ſome Regret; becauſe there are many Cenſorious and Ill-temper'd People in the World, who are ready to interpret that as an Accuſation, which is only Advice; and to catch at any thing which may ſerve them as an Handle to ſtrike at Clergy-men, though the thing be innocent in it ſelf, and be intended to quite different Purpoſes. It is ſome Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to me, that your Lordſhip is obliged, in ſome meaſure, to juſtifie me; and that the Faults which ſhall be diſcover'd in theſe Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, you have now made your own, by coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenancing of them, and making them appear by your own Directions. What Fortune ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever this Diſcourſe ſhall find abroad, I hope you your ſelf will be pleaſed to accept it this ſecond Time, as ſome (though a ſmall) Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, that I am</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips, In all Duty and Affection, Edw. Pelling.</signed> 
               <dateline>Petworth, <date>Octob. 20 1692.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:64350:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>1 Tim. 4. 16.</bibl>
               <q>Take heed unto thy ſelf, and unto thy Doctrine.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>NOT to diſpute about the Time, when; or about the Place, whence, this E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle was ſent by St. <hi>Paul;</hi> we may obſerve Three Things of the Perſon to whom it was directed.</p>
            <p>1. That he was intruſted with the Miniſterial Office by the ſpecial Deſignation of the Holy Ghoſt himſelf. St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of Propheſies which went before of him, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 18. mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by Prophecies, Divine Revelation, whereby <hi>Timothy</hi> was ſet apart for the work of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith St. <hi>Chryſoſtom;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chriſoſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in 1 Tim.</hi> 1. 18</note> by the particular Call, and immediate Appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Holy Ghoſt. For, the conducting of Souls being ſo great a Work, and the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterial Office ſo great a Dignity, God was pleaſed in thoſe Times to give ſpecial Directions by Divine Revelation, who ſhould have that weighty Truſt committed unto them. So St. <hi>Luke</hi> tells us, <hi>Acts</hi> 13. 2. that the Holy Ghoſt ſaid, <hi>Separate me</hi> Barnabas <hi>and</hi> Saul <hi>for the Work
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:64350:4"/> whereunto I have called them.</hi> And <hi>Clemens Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manus</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Clem. Ep. ad Cor. p.</hi> 54.</note> tells us expreſly, That the Apoſtles con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted Biſhops and Deacons by the Spirit's Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation; and having perfect Fore-knowledge (by Revelation) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (for ſo I<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 53.</note> conceive the place ſhould be read) they aſſigned to ſuch as were Ordained, their reſpective Cures<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Euſeb. Hiſt. Ec. Lib. 3. cap.</hi> 23.</note> and Charges Paſtoral. And <hi>Clemens Alexandri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> relates of St. <hi>John</hi> in particular, That as he viſited the Churches in <hi>Aſia,</hi> he made Clergy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of thoſe who were ſignified to him by the Holy Ghoſt. A power of <hi>Diſcerning Spirits,</hi> or of knowing Mens Hearts, was a ſpecial Gift in the beginning of Chriſtianity; and then, for the moſt part, Men were admitted into Holy Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders by God's ſpecial Appointment; which is meant by the word, Prophecy; and ſo was <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy</hi> choſen and ſet apart.</p>
            <p>2. And yet, <hi>Secondly,</hi> it is obſervable, that at that time <hi>Timothy</hi> was but a young man: Not one of the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a Novice lately converted to the Faith (for he had been ſome conſiderable time an Aſſiſtant to St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and a Companion in his Travels) but a Young Man in reſpect of his Age, and in compariſon of other Governors of the Church, who were generally Venerable, not only for their Holy Lives, but for their Hoary Heads alſo; and ſo were ſometimes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſcuouſly
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:64350:4"/> called, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Elders; not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſame Authority, but becauſe the like Gravity was common to them all. For this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who expreſt a particular<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Care and Tenderneſs for this his Son <hi>Timothy,</hi> was in a ſpecial manner concern'd, that no Man might <hi>deſpiſe his Youth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. As young as <hi>Timothy</hi> was, he was plac'd at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> as in his Epiſcopal See. <hi>Euſebius</hi> gives it us as a receiv'd Tradition, That he was the firſt Biſhop of that City; the Fathers at the Council of <hi>Chalcedon</hi> reckon ſo too; and indeed the two Epiſtles of St. <hi>Paul</hi> to him, wherein he was direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to govern the Church, to order Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matters, to Ordain Elders, and even to Judge and Cenſure them, do very plainly import, that he was inveſted with the Epiſcopal Authority; though it was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (to uſe the Expreſſion of <hi>Ignatius</hi> the Martyr concerning <hi>Dama,</hi> who was a Young Man, and a Biſhop too) the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of a Young Man, Ordination granted before the uſual time, by reaſon of his ſingular Merits.</p>
            <p>This, by the way, ſhews, that in the very be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of Chriſtianity, the Epiſcopal Power and Office was a diſtinct thing from that of Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters, and Superiour to it. For if that were true, which ſome would make us believe, that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:64350:5"/> an equality of Power did originally belong to all Miniſters of the Goſpel, and that in the firſt Ages, the Senior Presbyter was wont of courſe to ſucceed in the Precedency over the reſt, and was called Biſhop by the Courteſie of the College, though he was no more in Power than like the Chairman of an Aſſembly; I ſay, if it had been anciently and originally thus, it is not likely that ſo young a Man as <hi>Timothy</hi> would have been dignified with the Preheminence before his turn.</p>
            <p>But not to digreſs. Theſe things, my Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Brethren, I have briefly obſerv'd, that all may ſee what great Reaſon St. <hi>Paul</hi> had to direct <hi>Timothy,</hi> how he ſhould behave himſelf in the Houſe of God, which is the Church of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God, the <hi>Pillar and Ground</hi> of Truth, to uphold and Support it, and to exhibit it to the World.</p>
            <p>He, who was called to the weighty Office of Saving Souls, by the particular directions of the Holy Ghoſt: He, who was made one of the Angels of the Church, and had a conſiderable part of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire for his Dioceſs: He, who was to expect ſo much Contempt and Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition on all hands, and in his Youth was to encounter with the moſt formidable Wolves: He, who was to endure ſo many Difficulties,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:64350:5"/> and was to venture all in the moſt dangerous Times, and in the moſt Idolatrous and Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Place: He, who was to light many Families of the Earth to Heaven, and was accountable for his own Soul, and for many thouſand Souls beſides: He, who had no Comfort to depend upon, but the Teſtimony of a good Conſcience to bear him up in that His day, and in the day of God: He had the higheſt reaſon, to look ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry carefully to his Steps; to make it his only Study, how to Preach well, and to Live better; and to endeavour by all poſſible means of whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom Inſtructions, and an holy Example, to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the Ends of his high Calling; leſt, when he had Preach'd to others, he himſelf ſhould become a Caſt-a-way.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Paul</hi> therefore being uncertain when he ſhould ſee this young Labourer again, whom he had put lately into the Vineyard, ſent him, by Letter, divers neceſſary Inſtructions for the due Performance of his great Work: That he ſhould keep Faith, and a good Conſcience; that he ſhould ſettle the publick Service of God, who was to bleſs his Labours; that he ſhould ordain a Blameleſs Miniſtry, to aſſiſt him in his heavy Employment; that he ſhould provide againſt Seducing Spirits; that he ſhould be an Example to Believers; that he ſhould give Attendance to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:64350:6"/> Reading, and not neglect the Gift which had been given him by Prophecy; and divers ſuch like Directions more: All which ſeem to be ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med up briefly in theſe few Words, <hi>Take heed unto thy ſelf, and unto thy Doctrine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which Admonition doth, indeed, principally concern ſuch Church-men as <hi>Timothy</hi> was; ſuch as move in the higheſt Sphere, ſuch as caſt the moſt powerful, and the moſt ſpreading In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence: But yet we who are of a ſubordinate Rank, ſhould look upon it, as belonging, in a great meaſure, unto us alſo. For, though we muſt not uſurp that Authority and Honour which is the Right and Propriety of our Fathers, yet are we ſtrictly bound to take our ſhare of that Duty and Burthen which is common unto us all. And that this Admonition may be of the better uſe to us, for God's ſake, let us, with all poſſible Care and Diligence, obſerve both theſe Caveats in it. 1. Let us take heed unto our ſelves, as that which chiefly concerns our own Souls: Let us ſee that our own Lives be ſuch as do become Miniſters of God, and Preachers of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. 2. And then, Let us take heed unto our Doctrine too, as that which concerns the Souls of our Hearers: Let us ſee that it be ſuch as may have a good Influence upon them, and may ſerve effectually to build them up too in the moſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:64350:6"/> holy Faith. Theſe are the Parts of the Text, and of our Duty; and if we do perſevere in a due Care of theſe two Things, if we exerciſe our ſelves in them with Zeal, and employ our Time upon them with Diligence, we may hope, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all Diſcouragements, that, by the Grace and Bleſſing of God, we ſhall ſave our ſelves, and them that hear us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt, Let us take heed unto our ſelves;</hi> For we tread as if we were walking upon the very Ridge of a Church, where every Step we take is both viſible and dangerous; there is a Precipice on each Hand, and there are Eyes all round about us, and ſome too that may long to ſee us fall. In this Caſe we cannot be too cautious; and our only ſure Way is, to <hi>let our Light ſhine ſo before Men, that they may ſee our good Works;</hi> to be Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples to them, whether they will or no, to do our Part however; and by our Prudence, Piety, and ſignal Vertue, to cut off all Occaſion from ſuch as ſeek Occaſion againſt us. There is not a more odious, a more hurtful Creature in the World, than an Unconſcionable and Scandalous Clergy-man: One that holds a Taper behind him, to light all Men but himſelf: One that over-looks that Hell, which he pretends to ſhew others: One, whom neither the Senſe of God's Honour, nor the Dignity of his Sacred Function,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:64350:7"/> nor the Intereſt of Religion, nor the Dictates of Natural and Enlightned Conſcience, nor the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſneſs of Souls, nor the Shamefulneſs of Sin, nor the Terrors of a Judgment-day, can be ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to bring to a ſerious Conſideration of his Duty. Nor is any thing a greater Diſcredit to Religion, than that ſuch an unhallowed Mouth ſhould blow the Trumpet in the Sanctuary; or that ſuch Salt ſhould be uſed about the Sacrifices of the Temple, as is more noiſom and unſavoury, than what is taken out of a Dunghill. It is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to expreſs ſuch a Man's Guilt, or the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries and Miſchief which comes to Religion by it. One ſuch Clergy-man doth the Church more harm, than perhaps Twenty others may be able to do it good, by all their Cares, Pains, and Watchſulneſs.</p>
            <p>I would not have any uncharitable Man hope, that my Deſign is to caſt a Stone at any Reverend Perſon here. No, my Brethren; my purpoſe is, but to take the modeſt Freedom of a friendly Remembrancer; to repreſent that to you, which is in your own Religious Thoughts; to ſpeak your own Senſe, or ſomething near, though it be below it; and to lay before you ſome of thoſe Conſiderations, which I am ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to believe, you your ſelves are careful to act upon.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:64350:7"/>
            <p>Let us then take heed unto our ſelves, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you:</p>
            <p>1. For the Honour of our Profeſſion. I need not tell you how full the Ancient Chriſtians were, and even profuſe in their Encomiums of the Prieſthood, and how high they ſet it; ſome of them comparing the Sacerdotal with the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Regal Dignity. It was venerable in thoſe Times of Piety, and Chriſtian Simplicity: And though ſome went too far in their Notions and Expreſſions concerning this Matter, yet ſo far we ſhould, all of us, magnifie our Office (in this Senſe) as to count it no ſmall thing, that the God of <hi>Iſrael</hi> hath ſeparated us from the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to bring us near to himſelf, to do the Service of the Tabernacle of the Lord; as <hi>Moſes</hi> told thoſe Sons of <hi>Levi, Exod.</hi> 16. Of the whole Maſs of Mankind, none are ſegregated to be ſo near unto God, as the Diſpenſers of his Word and Sacraments; and therefore they are called, by way of peculiar Approbation, the Servants, the Miniſters, the Stewards, the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors of God. The Waſhings and Unctions under the Law, and the Impoſition of Hands under the Goſpel, were ſo many Rites of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrating and Separating Men to the ſpecial Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God; and this State of Separation we call <hi>Relative</hi> Sanctity, whereby Miniſters of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:64350:8"/> Holy Things become, after a more peculiar and eminent manner, <hi>Holy unto the Lord.</hi> And ſhould we, after all this, defile our ſelves with the Pollutions of the World, or have any Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip with the Works of the Fleſh, and the Works of Darkneſs; what ſhould we do, but deſecrate the thing which was ſolemnly hallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and bring our Souls under the intolerable Guilt of Profanation and Sacrilege? Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, I beſeech you: Such as ought to be the Uſe of Conſecrated Things, ſuch ought to be the Converſation of Conſecrated Perſons; as the one is to be ſacred, ſo the other is to be holy. We condemn thoſe who did formerly ſet up Heathen Idols in Chriſtian Churches, as <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate did: We abhor thoſe who did put the Blood of Toads into the holy Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lices, and ſuch other abominable Mixtures; as <hi>Epiphanius</hi> ſays the <hi>Gnoſticks</hi> did: We deteſt the Memory of thoſe, who, in Times of Perſecution, deliver'd up the <hi>Holy Bible</hi> to be burnt, as the <hi>Traditores</hi> did; and threw the Holy Sacrament to Dogs; as <hi>Optatus</hi> ſays the old <hi>Donatiſts</hi> did: And what ſhould we think of our ſelves, if, after the ſolemn Dedication of our Souls and Bodies to God's Uſe, and to the Miniſtration of Holy Things, we ſhould proſtitute our own ſacred Character, and abandon our ſelves to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:64350:8"/> Luſts and Impurities of the World? <hi>If any Man defile the Temple of God, him ſhall God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy; for the Temple of God is holy,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Paul, 1 Cor.</hi> 3. 17. This Temple we of the Clergy are, after a peculiar manner; and ſomething more: And what ſhall not we deſerve, if we ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>file our ſelves, where Temple, and Prieſt, and Altar, and Sacrifice ſhould meet in One? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, we ſee with Sorrow how low our Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is ſunk in the Eſteem of ſome People; nor is there any Way to redeem the Honour of it ſo effectually, as by that Gravity, and Exemplary Vertue, which are the proper and certain Means of adorning it. You know the Story in <hi>Joſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus,</hi> of <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great marching to <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joſeph. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiqu. lib. 11. cap.</hi> 8.</note> when he ſaw the Prieſts meeting him in their Robes, and <hi>Jaddus</hi> the High Prieſt in his Pontifical Habit, and with a Golden Frontlet on his Mitre, wherein the Name of God was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, the King, though enrag'd at <hi>Jaddus,</hi> was ſo tamed by Natural Conſcience, and by the Natural Senſe he had of Religion, that he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently did Obeyſance to God's Name, and ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Reverence to the High Prieſt for God's ſake. <hi>Jaddus</hi> took great heed to himſelf at that time: And truly, my Brethren, we cannot take a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Courſe to ſoften the Spirits of ſome wild and troubleſom Men in the World, than by letting
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:64350:9"/> them ſee what we have of God upon us; and by ſhewing them, not the bare Name, but the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of God, thoſe charming Vertues which reſemble the Perfections and Glories of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Nature, and which are the true and lively Characters of the Divine Nature. This (if any thing) muſt needs command Reverence from Men of Senſe; I dare ſay, will command it from all, who have a Senſe of Common, Moral Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, though they have very little of Revealed Religion.</p>
            <p>2. Let us, I beſeech you, take heed to our ſelves, not only to adorn our Profeſſion, but that we may be uſeful and beneficial <hi>in</hi> it. Though our great Buſineſs be like our bleſſed Saviour's, to go about <hi>doing Good,</hi> eſpecially to thoſe unto whom we are ſent; yet many times, and in many places, it is a very hard matter to do it, though we uſe our utmoſt En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours; becauſe it is no eaſie matter to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade Men, eſpecially to their Spiritual Good; a thing which doth not fall under the Invitation of their Senſes, as their Worldly Intereſt doth. Though we <hi>toil all the Night</hi> (as he ſaid, who was afterwards made a Fiſher of Men) yet ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times <hi>we take nothing,</hi> unleſs it be Weeds, which, comparatively, is as good as nothing. But I conſider what the Lord ſaid to his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:64350:9"/> at Sea, <hi>Joh.</hi> 21, 6, <hi>Caſt the Net on the Right Side of the Ship, and ye ſhall find; and then they were not able to draw it for the multitude of Fiſhes.</hi> This is often our Caſe; we take nothing, when, for want of Advertency, we caſt not on the Right Side: But when we do that, our La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours are ſucceſsful. But if a Man be unskil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, or utterly unmindful of his Buſineſs; cares not what he is, nor what he does; how can he hope to ſpeed, on which Side ſoever he caſteth his Net? How can he expect that God will hear his Prayers, or bleſs his Pains, or in any meaſure proſper the Work which he doth not duly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard himſelf? The nature of the thing will not allow him to expect it, becauſe People are more apt to be influenced by Example, than by In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction; the one is more obvious, and ſinks deeper than the other: And a good Sermon is loſt, and flung back upon a Man's Face, when his Life is irreligious. But if our People ſee us our ſelves expreſs the Power of Godlineſs, they will be the more apt to count it a ſerious thing, and the more capable of receiving holy Impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions from us. If they ſee us diligently attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Worſhip of God, grave, zealous, and devout at Prayer, they will be the more readily allur'd to lift up their own Hearts, and to ſet their Affections on Things above. If they ſee
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:64350:10"/> in us that Humility, that Meekneſs, that Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, that Charity, that Peaceableneſs of Mind, and thoſe other Vertues and Graces which we would form in their Hearts, and which are ſo amiable in the ſight of God and Man; if, I ſay, they behold the Beauty of them in us, they will be the more eaſily ſollicited to the Love and Practice of them. In ſhort; By God's Bleſſing, our good Examples will not be loſt, though our Exhortations may, what Diſcouragements ſoever we may meet with in our great Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking; how deaf or diſtemper'd ſoever the People may be, with whom we have to deal; and how little ſoever our Hopes may be for the preſent, the Innocence and Strictneſs of our Lives will, by God's Grace, one time or other, effectually work upon them: To be ſure, we ſhall have this great Comfort upon our Death<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beds, that we have acted as became Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and honeſt Paſtors; when their Comfort will be very little, to conſider, that we have left them without Excuſe. Whatever their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation may be, for Chriſt his ſake, let us take heed that we be not guilty of that which the great Exemplar of Holineſs laid to the Charge of the Scribes and Phariſees, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23. <hi>They bind heavy Burthens, and grievous to be born, and lay them on other Mens Shoulders; but they
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:64350:10"/> themſelves will not move them with one of their Fingers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. Theſe Conſiderations, my Brethren, affect the Conſcience, and we know our ſelves ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged in point of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> to take heed unto our ſelves upon theſe Accounts. Give me leave to add in the next place, that we muſt take heed to our ſelves in point of <hi>Prudence too.</hi> Vulgar People are not wont to conſider the Conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of things, but <hi>we</hi> ſhould; we ſhould look forward in all Caſes, and evermore conſider what will follow if we be careleſs of our ſelves, and unmindful of our Duty: We ſhould lay every thing to our Hearts before-hand. And what elſe, I beſeech you, will be the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, but this; that we ſhall ſcandalize our Friends, gratifie our Enemies, bring upon one another a common Reproach, and in the End expoſe our whole Church to God's Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments?</p>
            <p>God be bleſſed, notwithſtanding Faction and Vice, there are great Numbers of good People, who love the Ways of this our <hi>Sion;</hi> eſpecially where the Feet of thoſe who preach Salvation unto it, are beautiful. When they ſee (as it was ſaid of <hi>Origen</hi>) an admirable Harmony be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Doctrine and Life of a Clergy-man; when he is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:64350:11"/> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> ſpeaks, a Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation and Picture of good Living, and an animated Pandect of the Laws of Religion; then is the Church's Face amiable indeed, in the Eyes of all her Friends; and then every good Man, though he be illiterate, hath the ſame Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument to offer for our Church, that was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently uſed in defence of Chriſtianity, <hi>viz.</hi> the good Lives of the Profeſſors and Preachers of it. And this is ſometimes a more ready way to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince and confirm People, than Dint of Diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. But when they who ſhould be Patterns, blot their own Copy, how can we hope to ſee a good Tranſcript? In ſuch a Caſe we ſhould diſcourage even thoſe that love us; we ſhould make them aſhamed of thoſe Affections which they ſee ſo ill placed, and of that Confidence which they repoſe in Men, ſo contradictory to themſelves: And perhaps too we may occaſion ſome ſecret Jealouſie in our beſt Friends, that we our ſelves are not perſuaded of the Terrors of the Lord, when we expreſs ſo little Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion and Fear of them.</p>
            <p>Nor is this all: For any Man may ſee how many there are in the World that look upon us with an inſidious Eye, and watch for our Halt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> So that between Irreligion, and Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Hypocriſie, we are ſtill in danger.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:64350:11"/> And what an acceptable thing would it not be to ſuch, to diſcover any Flaws in the Lives of a Clergy, whoſe very Vertues they hate? And if we would ſtand only upon our own juſt Defence, nothing can be a greater Satisfaction or Security to us, <hi>to take heed unto our ſelves;</hi> this being a certain Way for us to keep a Conſcience void of Offence both to God and Man, and even towards our Enemies. And 'tis no inconſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able part of Chriſtian Prudence, to cut off all juſt Occaſion of Quarrel, eſpecially where Men ſeek it; and to miniſter no Grounds of Scandal in an uncharitable Age, when Scandals are apt to be taken, whether they be given, or no. What manner of Men ought we to be, when even our Righteouſneſs, and our good Works are an Eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſore? When Men will not be ſo juſt as to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don (at leaſt) our Vertues, we cannot expect they will be ſo merciful as to forgive us our Vices. Let us therefore behave our ſelves with ſuch Caution, that if Men will malign us, they may hate us for no other Cauſe, but for that we are Miniſters of True Religion; and then we need not be aſhamed, or diſcouraged, becauſe it was upon that ſole Account that the World hated our very Lord and Maſter before us.</p>
            <p>To this, let me add, that we ſhould take heed to our ſelves in defence of our Common Fame;
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:64350:12"/> for that always ſuffers by the Miſcarriages of a few (ſometimes by the Faults of ſome one) whoſe Immoralities ſome will be ſure to lay open, that they may defame all the reſt, whoſe Vertues and Merits they will as ſurely conceal. You know how, in the early Times of Chriſtianity, the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieties of the <hi>Simonians</hi> redounded to the preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of the whole Chriſtian Cauſe; thoſe Wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſes which they acted being, by the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, laid to the Charge of the whole Church, though (as <hi>Juſtin Martyr,</hi> in his Apology, tells us) they had nothing common with them, but only the general Name of Chriſtians. And ſo it is with us at this Day: Let one of our Members ſuffer in his Reputation, and (though it be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt that, in this Senſe, the whole Body ſhould ſuffer with him, yet) 'tis uſual for the Reflexion and Scandal to paſs upon all, without Diſcrimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; the Guilty and Innocent are ſlain toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: And ſo it comes to paſs, that both the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury which every particular Clergy-man ſuſtains by it is of great Concernment, and the Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage which the Publick ſuſtains too is irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable.</p>
            <p>But matter of Scandal is not the greateſt thing to be conſidered, though that be too great: There is ſomething of a higher, nature yet. Since <hi>Ephraim</hi> is againſt <hi>Manaſſeh,</hi> and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:64350:12"/> 
               <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> againſt <hi>Ephraim,</hi> and both againſt <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah,</hi> we ought to take very great heed, leſt by our Sins and Neglects God be provoked to be againſt us all. We have no reaſon to be confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that God will keep that Candleſtick ſafe and faſt in his Hand, whoſe Tapers yield not their due Light: And it is obſervable, that when thoſe Meſſages, in <hi>Apoc.</hi> 2. &amp; 3. ſo full of Admonitions and Threats, were ſent to the Seven Churches of <hi>Aſia,</hi> they were directed ſpecially to the ſeveral Angels (or Biſhops) of thoſe Churches (and, in all probability, <hi>Timothy</hi> was then one of them:) Which intimates to us, that it lieth very much in the Miniſtry of any Church, either to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, or to further and help on thoſe diſmal Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities, which are many times the Iſſue of Care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſs and Irreligion. Therefore, my Brethren, for God's Honour ſake, whoſe Authority and Character we have; for our Fellow-Chriſtians ſake, whom Charity obligeth us to regard, as Signets upon our Right Hand; for the Faith ſake, which was once, for all, delivered unto the Saints; for the Kingdom's ſake, in the Proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Peace whereof every particular Man's In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt is bound up; for the Churches Sake, which is the Mother of us all, and whom we are bound to Obey, Honour, and, if need requires, to be Victims for: Upon all theſe accounts, let
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:64350:13"/> us, the Clergy of this Church, give all poſſible diligence, that we may be blameleſs and unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provable; that we be Exemplars of Vertue and Holineſs to thoſe, whom God hath ſet us over; that we watch for their Souls, and that we may Execute our Office, and give an account at laſt with Joy.</p>
            <p>And before I ſhut up this point, I beg leave to recommend briefly to our common Chriſtian Care, theſe few particulars.</p>
            <p>1. That we often peruſe and conſider ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, thoſe Solemn Promiſes and Vows which we made at our Ordination; and look upon them as ſuch Sacred Tyes, as are not to be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd, but by our faithful Performances, and by our utmoſt Cares and Labours to the laſt gaſp.</p>
            <p>2. That we our ſelves be careful to walk, all of us, by the ſame Rule, and to mind the ſame thing, and to be knit together, like Brethren in an inviolable bond of Love and Friendſhip to one another; and all of us, to be inſeparably united in due Affection and Obedience, to our Learned and Conſcientious Dioceſan.</p>
            <p>3. That we feed the Flock of God, not for filthy Lucre, but of a ready Mind, out of an Honeſt Heart, and a pure Conſcience; and that we make our Charges throughly ſenſible (if we can) that we Act upon Principles of Conſcience
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:64350:13"/> and out of ſincere Love and Charity to them; and becauſe the Love of our common Saviour conſtrains us. St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> hath well obſerved, that when our Lord ask'd <hi>Peter, whether he</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. lib. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Loved him,</hi> and commanded him to Feed his Sheep; it was not, that he might find out <hi>Peter</hi>'s Affections to himſelf (for he knew his Heart) but that he might ſhew his own Affections and Love to his Church; and that he might Teach all Miniſters of the Goſpel, to expreſs the ſame Affections to his Church, by his own bleſſed Example.</p>
            <p>4. That in the diſcharge of our Miniſterial Office, for Love ſake, we apply our care and pains, as it is moſt ſuitable to particular Mens Neceſſities: Inſtructing the Ignorant, aſſiſting the Infirm, viſiting the Sick, comforting the Afflicted, admoniſhing Evil Doers; in Meekneſs inſtructing thoſe that oppoſe us, compaſſionate to the Needy, Patient and Merciful to Enemies, Candid towards the Imprudent, Juſt, Kind, Friendly, Gentle, Charitable, and Tenderly Affected towards all.</p>
            <p>5. That God may proſper the great Work in our Hands; it is to be wiſht, that we would daily open the Doors of our Churches, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite our Pariſhioners to meet us there conſtantly, for the Solemn Celebration of God's Service.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:64350:14"/> There a main part of our Buſineſs lies, to Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſe Youth, to Adminiſter the Sacraments of Chriſt's Body and Blood, and with one Mouth, and one Heart, to invocate the Goodneſs of God for a Bleſſing upon us all. And the oftner theſe things are done, the more ſhall we and our Charges be fixt in a courſe of Virtue and Piety; and the more will their Hearts be knit to us, as well as our Hearts to them.</p>
            <p>6. To which let me, I beſeech you, add, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Offence, that we uſe the Prayers of the Church, with that Reverence, Decorum, and Zeal, which is ſuitable to ſo ſolemn a Service. The Arguments againſt our Common Prayers are trifling, and will appear ſo every day more and more, if we our ſelves do but recommend them to others, by our own Devotion. 'Tis the ſlubbering of them over, after a haſty, cold, and uncouth manner; and ſometimes, with an affected and ungraceful Tone (Voice I cannot ſo well call it) 'tis this that has made our Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice-Book contemptible among ſome People, who conſider not the Excellent Contexture, and the True Chriſtian Spirit which is in the Prayers themſelves. And we ſhall be the more to blame, if we take not heed to remove this Objection, becauſe it is an Objection out of our own Mouths. Briefly then; we ſhould be careful to Read the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:64350:14"/> Publick Prayers with that Gravity and Concern'd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, with that Thoughtfulneſs and Deliberation, with that Attention and Preſence of Mind, and with that Fervency of Spirit, as if we were to give up the Ghoſt the next hour: And were all of us but Zealouſly intent upon this, I dare ſay there would be no need of further Arguments or Oratory, to beſpeak the Affections of People to our Service, or to render it Venerable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> I beg the excuſe of this Reverend Aſſembly, that I have been ſo particular and prolix upon the former part of my Text, of <hi>taking heed to our ſelves;</hi> becauſe it is indeed the Principal thing; that which is a moſt neceſſary ingredient to make our Doctrine operative and effectual; and conſidering, that what hath been ſaid already, has taken up more time than I thought it would have coſt us, I muſt diſpatch this next thing with a quick Hand; <hi>Take heed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy Doctrine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I muſt not take the Confidence here, to direct this Learned Body; and yet there are ſome things to be borrowed of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> which may be of very great uſe to us all, though Miniſtred by the unworthieſt Hand.</p>
            <p>1. Firſt, That our Doctrine be ſuch, as Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally tendeth to promote a Good Life; Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, which is according to Godlineſs, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 3.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:64350:15"/> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 10. wholeſome, Sana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory Doctrine; ſuch Truths as are Reſtoratives and Preſervatives of Subſtantial Religion. Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary Diſputes, lofty Speculations, fine, airy Deſcants, and the like; though there may be Truth in them, and profitable Truth too in its kind, yet they are quite out of our way, whoſe Buſineſs is to Teach People to hold the Faith in a pure Conſcience. Our Diſcourſes therefore, are to be in ſome meaſure or other Practical; and the more Practical our Matter is, the plainer our Method, the eaſier our Style, the clearer our Expreſſions, the more obvious our Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and the more ſolid and inſtructive our Notions are, the better ſhall we do the parts of Conſcientious and Skilful Preachers, and the more Profitable will our Diſcourſes be; witneſs, for all, that one Excellent Book, the <hi>Whole Duty of Man;</hi> the Book that hath done ſuch Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Good in the World; and that not only by the Gravity of the Matter, but by the uſefulneſs of the Style; the Contexture of that Book, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ordered by the moſt Pious and Judicious Author ſo, that the whole is Practical, Plain, Inviting, Adapted to every Man's Reaſon, eaſie to be underſtood by People of all Capacities.</p>
            <p>2. <hi>Let us take heed,</hi> Secondly, that our Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine be the True and Genuine Doctrine of the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:64350:15"/> Goſpell; Uncorrupt, found Speech, that cannot be Condemned, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> directed <hi>Titus, Tit.</hi> 2. 8. Many Errors are abroad in the World, which have Tainted the Truths of the Goſpel, with a mixture of Humane Traditions, and Private Fancies. To keep our ſelves and our Flocks from infection, theſe two things, in ſhort, are very adviſeable.</p>
            <p>1. Firſt, that in all Points we diligently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult, and have an eye upon the Faith of the moſt Primitive Ages. There is a conciſe way (ſaith St. <hi>Cyprian</hi>) for Religious and ſimple mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 74.</note> Men to remove an Error, and to find out and diſcover the Truth. And what way is that? Why, by going to the Spring, to the Head and Original of Divine Tradition. As, if you would find where the fault lyes, when the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter fails, the readieſt courſe, is to repair to the Fountain, to ſee whether the fault be there, or in the Aquaeduct; ſo when Truth fails, or becomes uncertain, the ſureſt way, is to go to its Original, to the Goſpel of Chriſt, and to Apoſtolical Tradition. And certainly, the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Judgment we ſhall be able to make in all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial points, the nearer we go to the Fountain-Head, and the more narrowly we obſerve, what condition things were in Anciently, in thoſe Channels which were next to the Fountain. Had
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:64350:16"/> this courſe been well and carefully followed, abundance of unhappy Controverſies might have been prevented, which in theſe latter times have made ſuch vaſt diſturbances in the Church. 2. Next to the Doctrines of the Old Catholick Church; let us, for God's ſake, take great heed to the Doctrine of our own Church in particular, which hath with the greateſt care followed the Ancient pattern. I mention this the rather, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſome have preſumed to repreſent us to the unthinking part of the World, as Friends to ſome Foreign Doctrines; Doctrines brought hither, ſome from <hi>Rome,</hi> others from <hi>Irenopolis,</hi> An Accuſation full of Uncharitableneſs; and I am confident, of Falſhood; it being impoſſible for thoſe, who are profeſt Members of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and have often Subſcribed to her Articles and whole Conſtitution, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain or favour ſuch pernicious Errors, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſuch horrible Hypocriſie, as no Man of Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor and Juſtice will ſuppoſe, ſo many Guides of Souls can be guilty of. But ſometimes there is no fence againſt Calumny; and we muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent our ſelves with the Anſwer of a Good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience in ſuch a caſe. Nevertheleſs, my Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, 'tis Prudential and Neceſſary for us, to keep at a great diſtance from every Opinion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which in the Eyes of diſcerning and good Men<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:64350:16"/> looks like Heretical; and not to come within the reach of Suſpition; for it is not enough for us to be Innocent, unleſs we appear ſo.</p>
            <p>To conclude; let us take heed, that our<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine be the True Word of God; that it be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to the Senſe of the Ancient Church, where the Holy Scripture is not plain; that it be a means to form in Peoples Hearts, thoſe Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, wherein the Life and Subſtance of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on doth conſiſt, things which are Honeſt, Juſt, Pure, Lovely, and of good Report; that it aim at thoſe Virtues chiefly, which are productive of many more; as, a Devout Temper, Humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Charity<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Sobriety, and a peaceable Diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition; that it help to promote the Practice of thoſe Duties, wherein our Charges are moſt negligent and moſt wanting: That it tend to the Publick Good of the Church and State, to which we all belong; that it Teach People to be orderly, quiet, and obedient in all things law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; that it be not mixt with any mean Deſigns of our own, but that God's Glory, and the good of Souls, be the end of Preaching, doing the work of God, as Faithful Servants of God, and as in the ſight of God; that our Doctrine be deliver'd with Gravity and Zeal, with Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Spirit, with Simplicity of Mind, with Application to thoſe Sins which are moſt reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:64350:17"/> and infectious, with that impartiality and Honeſty, which becomes Men who are Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards of God's Myſteries.</p>
            <p>And as long as we addict our ſelves to Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter before God after this manner, we ſhall have all the Reaſon to hope, that he will bleſs our Miniſtrations. Nor ſhould we be diſcourag'd, if we preſently find not the Succeſs we deſire. For Grace and Virtue grows, like the painful Husbandman's Seed, by degrees, by little and little, firſt the Blade, then the Ear, at laſt the full Corn, and a good Crop. The Religion of our Lord Jeſus is, in ſome points, ſo much above the Carnal Reaſon of Unregenerate Men, in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ſo contrary to their Corrupt Inclinations, that it requires Time and Labour to bring them to the true Sence, Love and Practice of it. If we be diligent and aſſiduous; God, whom we ſerve, will be Glorified, our Church will rife in its Honour and Intereſt, our Charges will be Edified, and by God's Gracious Aſſiſtance we ſhall Save our ſelves, and them that hear us<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Which, that every one of us may do, God of his Mercy grant, for Chriſt Jeſus his ſake.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
